CENK AKARSU

Senior Software Engineer

Amsterdam, Netherlands | +31 6 21313756 | cenk@cenkakarsu.com | linkedin.com/in/cenkakarsu

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A Senior Software Engineer and tech lead with over 13 years of experience, including significant leadership roles at **Meta** and **Microsoft**, where I **architected and delivered planet-scale**, **financial-grade cloud systems**. Specialized in distributed systems, fintech platforms, SOX compliance, and high-throughput real-time transaction processing. Proven leader in **guiding cross-functional teams**, **enhancing regulatory compliance**, **optimizing developer productivity**, **and ensuring audit readiness**.

CORE SKILLS

• Distributed Systems & Cloud Architecture • Financial Systems & SOX Compliance • Real-time Transaction Processing • Front-End & Back-End Development • Mentorship & Technical Leadership • Microservices & Scalability

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

META

Senior Software Engineer (Tech Lead) | 01.2022 - Present | Amsterdam. The Netherlands

- Led the end-to-end project lifecycle for the Close Platform, a mission-critical system instrumental in Meta's monthly financial close, directly impacting financial reporting accuracy.
- Architected and successfully delivered technical solutions by gathering requirements from financial stakeholders, ensuring robust and compliant systems that process over 120 billion dollars of revenue per year.
- **Guided and mentored team members,** fostering engineering excellence and driving technical decisions to meet stringent demands of financial operations.

MICROSOFT

Senior Software Engineer | 05.2018 - 11.2021 | Dublin, Ireland

- Developed and maintained full-stack solutions for **Microsoft 365** enterprise applications serving **millions of global** users.
- Built highly scalable, multi-regional microservices using Azure Service Fabric, handling high requests per second (RPS).
- Led UX/UI development, enhancing application usability through intuitive, accessible React and TypeScript interfaces.
- Architected and built internal tools and platforms, including a comprehensive monitoring dashboard, to improve
 engineering productivity and track the health of services across all regions.
- Mentored team members on React and TypeScript best practices and onboarded new engineers to the team's tech stack and development processes.

GARANTI TECHNOLOGY

Senior Software Engineer | 02.2013 – 04.2018 | Istanbul, Turkey

• Spearheaded R&D initiatives using NLP, Named Entity Recognition (NER), and machine learning for document classification.

- **Developed a comprehensive Audit Management System**, streamlining task and resource management for Garanti Bank's Audit Board.
- Engineered scalable intranet and portal systems serving tens of thousands of bank employees nationwide.

ETIYA INFORMATION TECHNOLOGIES

Software Engineer | 10.2012 - 02.2013 | Istanbul, Turkey

• Developed "Somemto," a semantic analysis and NLP-driven social media monitoring platform providing actionable insights for customer engagement.

TRAKYA UNIVERSITY IT DEPARTMENT

Software Developer | 02.2009 - 06.2012 | Edirne, Turkey

- Developed a patented Braille alphabet learning tool for visually impaired children (hardware and software).
- Created academic performance evaluation systems and various departmental websites using ASP.NET and SQL Server.

EDUCATION

Bahcesehir University | Ph.D (Doctor of Philosophy) | Computer Engineering | 01.2017 - Discontinued

 Research Areas: Deep Learning, Recommender Systems, Data Mining, Big Data, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing

Yildiz Technical University | Master of Science | Computer Engineering | 10.2012 - 04.2016

- Thesis: "Predicting Turkish TV Ratings Using Twitter Data".
- Research Areas: Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning, Text Classification, Collective Learning, Data Mining

Trakya University | Bachelor of Science | Computer Engineering | 10.2008 - 06.2012

• Graduated 4th in class, GPA: 3.5/4

PUBLICATIONS

Turkish TV Rating Prediction with Twitter

24th IEEE Conference on Signal Processing and Communications Applications, 16-19 May 2016, Zonguldak Turkey

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES AND TECHNOLOGIES

Hack, React, C# .NET, Service Fabric, Angular, Typescript, Python, Javascript, Java, SQL, Powershell, PLSQL, Flutter

AWARDS

- Microsoft Ireland Fix & Hack & Learn Awards:
 - Best Contribution to Open-Source (2020 and 2021)
 - Best Learn Award (2018, 2020)
 - Best Fix Award (2019)
- Microsoft Global Hackathon Country Winner (Ireland, 2018)

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

- Languages: Turkish (Native), English (Fluent IELTS Academic: 8/9, PTE Academic: 87/90)
- Volunteer and board member of Garanti Technology Search and Rescue Team (GTAK)
- Passionate guitar player